Okay בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today's דף daf is ע"ה, ayin hey,
עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah 75, the penultimate דף daf of the מסכת.
Masechet. We pick up on ע"ה עמוד א' ayin hey amud aleph
three lines from the top, איתמר. itmar. We are discussing details of
the משנה Mishna which spoke about a wine press that you bought
from non-Jews and depending on whether it was made with wood or
stone or pottery and whether it was pitched or not pitched, different
ways of cleansing it. It absorbed only in cold so to not
absorb in hot so you can don't, it's not the normal type
of כשרות kashrut we are used to and different types of ways
of drying or scouring or peeling it and so on. So the
case in the משנה Mishna sort of spoke about the first case
of the משנה Mishna which it was stone and it was and
it was lined with pitch and it says you dry it and
there was a debate between or like רב Rav and שמואל, Shmuel,
excuse me, רב Rav and רבה בר בר חנה, Rabbah bar bar
Chana, mentioning water and ashes and the גמרא Gemara said it was
really both of them combined. Water plus the ashes would make a
type of a soap, a cleanser, and that's how you would scour
it and dry it out. So now the גמרא Gemara is just
going to finish up with some specific details about this and then
we will move on. איתמר itmar it was taught, בי רב משמיה
דרב, Bei Rav mishmei deRav, in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב Rav
in the name of רב, Rav, אמרי תרתי תלת, amri tarti tlas,
two or three steps in terms of this drying out. So there's
a whole long רש"י Rashi and תוספות Tosafot about exactly how to
read the next few lines of the גמרא. Gemara. We're just going
to go with the first read of רש"י Rashi for simplicity's sake.
So רש"י Rashi says that if you are dealing with with one
that is moist that still has some moisture of wine on the
surface, then it is two steps. You do the ashes because I
guess they combine with the wine, you know, they need moisture or
it absorbs the moisture and then you add water and and you
scour it and you're done. If you're dealing with dry, ironically it
needs three stages even though it actually has doesn't have stuff on
the surface, does not have wine on the surface. You might think
it needs less but maybe you know it seems like you always
need liquid to get started. So if you're starting with something dry
you need three stages: water, ashes, and then finally water again. The
ashes have to always be followed by water. Okay, so that's two
or three. ושמואל אמר תלת ארבע, VeShmuel amar tlas arba, and שמואל
Shmuel says no, three or four, and the way רש"י Rashi basically
says this is that שמואל Shmuel adds a step. He needs another
round of ashes and water. So if it's
wet you do you do you do ashes and water, you know,
because you always start with the moisture of the wetness and then
you do ashes and water and then you do another ashes. Okay,
because you need two steps of two stages with the ashes and
of course you would need a water after that but we're not
mentioning the water after that for some reason. And if it's dry
then you do water, ashes, water, ashes. Okay, so you basically need
two stages of ashes, three or four. בסורא מתנו הכי, Besura masnu
hachi, that's how they taught it in סורא. Sura. בפומבדיתא מתנו בי
רב אמרי, BePumbedisa masnu Bei Rav amri, but in פומבדיתא Pumbedisa they
said that in the ישיבה Yeshiva of רב Rav they would say,
משמיה דרב תלת ארבע, mishmei deRav tlas arba, three or four, which
שמואל Shmuel had just said. So two stages of ashes. With wet
it's ashes, water, ashes, and then there's going to be another water
to rinse it out but we're not mentioning it. And with dry
it's water, ashes, water, ashes, and then again another water to rinse
it out but we're not
but we're not mentioning that. Okay. משמיה דרב
תלת ארבע ושמואל אמר ארבע
וחמשא. Mishmei deRav tlas arba veShmuel amar arba v'chamesha. שמואל Shmuel says
four and five, okay, and the way we're going to see it
explained in or the way the way what רש"י Rashi here says
that means is that שמואל Shmuel agrees with רב Rav and he's
just adding counting the last water that is going to be done.
ולא פליגי, V'lo pligi, and they don't debate. מר כחשיב מיא בתראי
ומר לא כחשיב מיא בתראי. Mar kachashiv maya basraye umar lo kachashiv
maya basraye. So רב Rav and שמואל Shmuel both agree that you
need two stages, okay, and the question is do you just count
the last water. So רב Rav who says three and four would
be saying if you start with moist you do ashes because again
you apparently always need the liquid first, ashes then you do water,
ashes. Okay, that's three and then there's one more water to rinse
it out but we're not counting it. And if it's dry you
do water, ashes, water, ashes, that's four and then one more water
to rinse it out which we're not talking about and שמואל Shmuel
says we are going to talk we are going to count that
last one so that's how you're going to get four and five.
Okay, not too conceptually interesting. We will end there. I mean that's
the end of that discussion. Now, בעי מיניה מרבי אבהו, Ba'ei minei
meRabbi Abbahu, they asked רבי אבהו Rabbi Abbahu
on taskering other parts of the wine press or you know which
and how do you do that? הרי שהיו גיתו ובית הבד טמאים.
Harei shehayu gito uveit habad tmeim. I'm sorry, skipped a line. בעי
מיניה מרבי אבהו הני גורגי דארמאי, Ba'ei minei meRabbi Abbahu hani gorgi
de-aramai, these sort of wicker baskets or wine baskets of the non-Jews,
you know, the the thing the frame that was used to keep
all of the grapes together when you would do the pressing, מה,
ma, what? the story. It sounds pretty much like our משנה, Mishna,
but you know that sounds like isn't that sort of the same
as the גת? Gat? But again, each one of these is probably
dealt with a slightly different מציאות. Metzius. Anyway, what would you do?
So אמר ליה רבי אבוס, Amar lei Rabbi Abos, רבי אבוס Rabbi
Abos said, תני תו, Tani tu, we taught in the ברייתא, Baraita,
הרי שהיו גיתו ובית הבד טמאים. Harey shehoyu gito uveit habad tmei’im.
If your, this is a case by טהרות, Taharos, not by wine,
but again, it's always worth noting that, you know, the discussion about
wine and a non-Jew touching it is like he's מטמא, metamei, we've
used beforehand, you know, used the idea of טומאה, tumah, we've discussed
questions about if there's a ספק, safek, learning parallels from טומאה tumah
when it discussed somebody who wanted to make kosher wine,
המטהר את יינו. hamataher et yeino. So it's very interesting all of
the analogies that are being made and the parallels. So here it's
a case where you bought your winepress or olive press from an
עם הארץ Am Ha’aretz who does everything as טמא. tamei. You have
to assume it's all טמא. tamei. Now you want to start producing
kosher, you know, olive oil and wine that's טהור. tahor. But you've
got all of this wine, you know, residue in the winepress and
olive residue in the olive press. Similar type of a question: how
are you going to get rid of it? Very similar to our
cases. So וביקש לעשותם בטהרה, uvikesh la’asosam betahara, now you want to
start making this with it's טהור. tahor. So here's what you have
to do. הדפין והדשין והלולבין, Hadapin vehadashim vehalulavin, if you're dealing with
the doors, meaning like the planks that are used for pressing the
olives or the grapes, and הדשין, hadashim, רש״י Rashi says that actually
means the גת gat itself, the winepress itself, the thing that actually
holds holds the grapes, והלולבין vehalulavin are like the, you know, like
the palm branches that are used as brooms to sweep the grapes
back into the pile. So all those things, מדיחן, midichan, it's enough
to rinse them, which is interesting because if one of them refers
to the winepress itself, you know, our משנה Mishna says you have
to dry it. But again, our משנה Mishna was talking about that
they were plastered, this isn't plastered, so every one is a little
different. Okay, but if it's those things, you rinse them. והעקלים של
נצרים ושל בצבוץ, Veha’akalim shel netsarim veshel bitzbutz, but if you're actually,
if you're dealing with the pressing basket, and that's the עקלים. akalim.
So apparently, for this is considered the same as, you know, this
is what we were talking about before with the גורגי, gorgi, you
know, is the עקלים. akalim. רש״י Rashi says that those are the
same. So apparently the גת gat itself, the winepress itself, which we
said rinsing it, and that was what was being discussed in our
משנה, Mishna, was where the wine collected.
But this עקלים, akalim, or what was called before גורגי, gorgi, the
wicker basket, is where you would like collect the grapes into a
type of wicker basket, and there's where you would, the beam would
push down on them, and that's where the actual wine would get
pressed. Okay? So in that type of a case, there's more pressure
and you know than just the vat where it gets collected, so
that's going to need to be kashered better. So
העקלים של נצרים, ha’akalim shel netsarim, so if they are made of
palm leaves, ושל בצבוץ, veshel bitzbutz, or בצבוץ, bitzbutz, which is like
hemp, okay, מנגבן, menagvan, then you have to dry it. It's not
enough to just rinse it. And we've discussed the whole thing with
ashes and water and so on. ושל שיפא ושל גמי, Veshel shifa
veshel gemi,
but if it is bullrush or reeds, then מישנן י״ב חודש. meyasnan
yod beis chodesh. You have to leave them for 12 months. So
this is, you know, things that people talk about like, you know,
China, 12 months, etc. That's a whole other discussion, but it learns
some of the idea that you might be able to wait 12
months, and that'll change the status, is learned from here, although it's
a big difference because here everything is absorbed in cold, and the
question is: can you even apply this 12-month thing to things that
absorbed hot? Okay? But here we are seeing that if it's made
of these other things, it's not enough to do some drying. The
stuff gets, you know, absorbed deep in, and the only way that
moisture is going to get out is if you leave it for
12 months. Okay? So what have we said? We said that certain
things that are just into casual contact, let's say, with the grapes
or with the wine, it's enough to rinse them. Okay? And that
would even include the vat itself. But things that are used to
like, you know, to like where the wine is actually being pressed,
the עקלים, akalim, okay, which is the same as the גורגי gorgi
before, that needs to actually be based on the material either to
dry it out like with the water and the ashes or the
12 months. All right. רבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, Rabban Shimon Ben
Gamliel omer, רבן שמעון בן גמליאל Rabban Shimon Ben Gamliel says,
מניחן מגת לגת ומבד לבד. menichan migat legat umibad lebad. Not 12
months, but from one, you know, one pressing of wine to the
next pressing of wine or one pressing of olives to the next
pressing for the next year. So גמרא Gemara says, I don't understand,
if it's the next year and this is seasonal and it's once
a year, היי תנא קמא, hai tanna kamma, that's what the תנא
קמא tanna kamma just said. No, איכא בינייהו
חורפי ואפלי. ika beinaihu chorfi ve’afli. No, it matters because sometimes you
have an early season or a late season. So even if you
wait to, you know, the time of the beginning of the next
season, the next year, that might be less or more than 12
months, depending on if it's an earlier or late season. Okay. רבי
יוסי אומר, Rabbi Yossi omer, רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi says, הרוצה לטהרן
מיד, harotzeh letaheran miyad, now let's say you don't want to wait
the 12 months and you've got these things, you know, that absorbed
a lot, so מגעילן ברותחין. magilan berotchin.
So then now you can use the type of thing you use
when you're kashering stuff that absorbs with hot, you can immerse them
in boiling hot water,
או חולטן במי זיתים, o choltan bimei zeitim, or you can like
use hot olive
oil, the water that was used for scalding the olives, for cooking
the olives, because you have to cook the olives in order to
soften them. Olives are very hard the way they grow. So that
water, if you scald them in that water, I don't know why
specifically that water, anyway but that will kasher them right away. Okay.
במי זיתים. bimei zeitim. ורבן שמעון בן גמליאל אומר, veRabban Shimon ben
Gamliel omer, now Rabban Shimon ben Gamliel again speaks up and he
says this time in the name of Rabbi Yose, no, מניחן תחת
צינור שמימיו מקלחים, menichan tachat tzinor shemeimav mekalchim,
you put them under running water like under a pipe that the
water is pouring out, או במעיין שמימיו רודפים, o bemaayan shemeimav rodfim,
or with a wellspring that the water is running. Okay. וכמה? vekama?
And how long do you leave them there? And again I guess
the constant hitting of water is going to pull out the absorbed
moisture. And how long is it? עונה, ona, an ona. We'll talk
about what an ona is. It's basically going to be 12 hours.
Okay, so there you go, different ways that you kasher something to
get to that's was used for tamei stuff. And the stuff that
is used both where the wine is the baskets where it's being
pressed, it absorbs more, and based on the material it might be
that it just needs to be dried with the ashes, but it
might need something much more vigorous: 12 months, running water, scalding, etc.
Okay. כדרך שאמרו ביין נסך כך אמרו בטהרות. kederech sheameru beyayin nesech
kach ameru betaharos. And the ברייתא Braita ends by saying the same
way they said this about wine, they said it about taharos. So
the גמרא Gemara says, כלפי לייא? klapi laya? Where is this going
towards? Like this is that didn't make sense. It's going in the
opposite direction. בטהרות קיימינן. betaharos kayiminan. We're talking about taharos. It says
you want to now use this wine press or or you know
or olive press for you know
to make tahor wine or olive oil. So we're talking in the
context of taharos, not in the context of yayin nesech. אלא איפוך,
ela ipuch, reverse it. What it means is, כדרך שאמרו בטהרות כך
אמרו ביין נסך. kederech sheameru betaharos kach ameru beyayin nesech. That this
ברייתא Braita that is talking about taharos and how do you kasher
it for
taharos, you would do the same thing when it came to wine.
Okay, so it's explicit, first of all, you know, obviously very similar
realities. You've got an olive press or a wine press and you
want to now use it in a way that's more kosher, and
the kashering is the same. And the ברייתא Braita explicitly says that
the same thing you do for taharos, you do here. And that
answers the question that Rabbi Abahu was asked about these wicker baskets
that the wine is pressed in, how you would kasher it. Okay.
Now the גמרא Gemara says, כמה עונה? kama ona? And how much
is this ona? So אמר רבי חייא בר אבא אמר רבי יוחנן,
amar Rabbi Chiya bar Abba amar Rabbi Yochanan, או יום או לילה,
o yom o layla, either a day or a night. Okay.
ורבי חנה שאינה, veRabbi Chana Sheina, Rabbi Chana of Sha'an presumably, ואמרי
לה רבי חנה בר שאינה veamri lah Rabbi Chana bar Sheina or
that was the name of his father, אמר רבה בר בר חנה
אמר רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, חצי
יום וחצי לילה. chatzi yom vechatzi layla. No, not a day or
night, but half the day and half the following night. All right.
ואמר רבי שמואל בר רב יצחק ולא פליגי. veamar Rabbi Shmuel bar
Rav Yitzchak velo pligi. They're not really debating because it doesn't really
have to be specifically daytime or night time. We're talking about how
many hours. הא בתקופת ניסן ותשרי, ha betkufas Nissan veTishrei, when you
say day or night, you're talking about it's the summer solstice or
the excuse me the spring or the the vernal or the autumnal
equinox, so that's every the day and night is all 12 each
is exactly 12 hours. הא בתקופת תמוז וטבת, ha betkufas Tammuz veTeves,
but if you're dealing in the summer or the winter, then the
days are either very short or very long and the nights are
the reverse. So if you want to get 12 hours there, you
say half the day and half the night. Bottom line is you
have to leave it under this running water for 12 hours. Okay.
אמר רבי שמואל בר יצחק ולא פליגי. amar Rabbi Shmuel bar Yitzchak
velo pligi. I'm sorry, I just said. אמר רב יהודה, amar Rav
Yehuda, הני רבקי דארמאי, hani rivki deArmai,
דמזייא
מדיחן. demazya medichan. So these רבקי, rivki, which Rashi says is a
type of a sieve, like a type of a bag, a sack
that you would put in
the lees of the wine, the grape skins and so on, and
you would try to squeeze out the remaining wine from them. Okay.
So demazya if they're made of hair, מדיחן, medichan, then you just
dry them, they don't really absorb. I don't even know why you
have to do the medichan if that means ashes and water, I
don't you know does it absorb anything? But okay. דעמרא, deamra, if
however you know it is made of of wool, מנגבן, menagvan, then
you have to, I'm sorry, מדיחן medichan just means just rinse them,
excuse me. Right. So if it's made of hair, then you just
rinse them because it doesn't really absorb at all. And if it's
made of wool and it it absorbs, מנגבן, menagvan, then you have
to dry it out. That's the more vigorous thing with the ashes
that really absorb that you have to dry it out. דכיתנא, dechitna,
if it's made however of flax that really absorbs, מישנן, meyashnan, you
have to let them get old. Okay. ואיכא, veika, which might mean
like the 12 years 12 months like we just said. ואיכא קטרי,
veika kitrei, and if there are knots in it, שרי להו, sharei
lehu, you have to undo the knots because you know that'll keep
the stuff will be buried with like you know you have to
expose the material so that all the stuff gets out when you're
drying it out. Whatever you're doing: rinsing it or you know drying
it
out. now baskets and strainers דארמאי d'arama'ei of the non-Jews so again
we seem to always be talking about very similar things but anyway
דחיתי de-chiti if it's made out of string
that are plated דחיתי בחבלי דצרי de-chiti be-chavlei de-tzari if it's like
if it is like woven with you know strips from from a
palm tree מדיחן madichan then it is enough to just rinse again
then it does not really absorb. Top of ע"ה עמוד ב' Ayin
Hey Amud Bet
דצפצא de-tzaftza לנגבן lenagvan if it is made out of you know
things of צפצא tzaftza which Rashi says is a type of of
a reed then that acts that absorbs more so you have to
dry it out. דקיתנא de-kitna if it's made of flax מישנן meyashnan
okay same idea you have to dry it out and let it
get old again presumably 12 months. ואיכא בהו קטרי ve-ika behu kitrei
and if there are knots שרי להו shari lehu you have to
undo the knots. All right.
איתמר itmar it was taught so we're finally done with all of
those specifics about how you dry and kasher things. All right. It
was taught.
אמר שהושיט ידו לגת amar she-hoshit yado le-gat so now we're going
to move from again we're moving back and forth from the study
of from the wine of יין נסך yayin nesech and סתם יינם
stam yeinam to the issue of עם הארץ am ha-aretz and touch
and tumah. So an עם הארץ am ha-aretz sticks his hand into
the wine press
ונגע באשכולות ve-naga be-eshkolot and he touches one of the clusters of
grapes okay that were sort of lying there you know on top
of the wine. רבי ורבי חייא Rebbi ve-Rabbi Chiya so it's a
debate of Rebbi and Rabbi Chiya. חד אמר אשכול וכל סביבותיו טמאין
chad amar eshkol ve-chol sevivotav tmein he made tamei the cluster itself
he touched the cluster and the stuff in the immediate surrounding area
is tamei. Again it's not exactly clear how you define what that
radius is and if you say some of it is tamei then
how do you cordon it off from the rest okay but we
can we'll talk about that. וכל הגת כולה טהורה ve-chol ha-gat kula
tehora but the rest of the whole wine press is tahor.
וחד אמר כל הגת כולה נמי טמאה ve-chad amar kol ha-gat kula
nami tmeia no no no when you touch that everything is in
contact with everything else so you made so he made everything tamei.
So now the Gemara says like this. ולמאן דאמר אשכול וכל סביבותיו
טמאין וכל הגת טהורה u-le-man d'amar eshkol ve-chol sevivotav tmein ve-chol ha-gat
tehora so if you say that it's just the cluster but the
remaining and the area surrounding but the rest of the wine press
is tahor מאי שנא מהא דתנן mai shna me-ha di-tnan how is
it different from that which we taught שרץ שנמצא בריהיים sheretz she-nimtza
be-reychaim if you have a you know a dead rodent that causes
tumah okay that was found you know in the in the olive
press אינו מטמא אלא מקום מגעו eino metamei ela mekom maga'o it
only the things that it is directly
touching and if he was touching some olives and it only makes
those olives tamei it doesn't make all of the surrounding olives tamei
okay.
ואם
היה משקה מהלך הכל טמא ve-im haya mashke mehalech ha-kol tamei but
if there was you know like a a layer of olive oil
that was you know covering everything then if it touches then that
thing it touches you know that olive oil connects everything and makes
it like one unit and when it touches something it makes everything
tamei so we have the same thing here you know we have
the wine that is totally in the wine vat so why when
you touch the cluster does it not make everything tamei. ואם
היה משקה מהלך הכל טמא
ve-im haya
mashke mehalech ha-kol tamei so if there was if there was liquid
olive oil flowing everything is tamei. The Gemara says no there's a
difference. התם לא מפסיק ולא מידי hatam lo mafsik ve-lo midi there
nothing is interrupting the flow of the liquid okay the liquid connects
and is in contact with like you know with everything else. הכא
מפסי אשכולות hacha mafsei eshkolot but here the actual cluster itself sort
of you know holds back the flow of the wine. The wine
is not one continuous amount of like you know wine in the
vat. So again I don't I don't really understand the exact מציאות
metziut it doesn't seem like you've got a tub full of wine
and a little cluster on top then everybody would agree everything is
tamei. It seems like you've got a bunch of clusters you know
and so there could be wine that is trapped immediately around you
know but there's other clusters there this is the way I imagine
it you know but it's not that the whole wine is in
one unit with everything else and that can explain why the area
immediately surrounding it but not the rest but again I don't fully
understand the מציאות metziut that we're talking about. Okay. אמרו להו רבנן
לרב ירמיה ואמרי לה לבריה דרב ירמיה
amru lehu rabanan le-Rav Yirmiyah
ve-amrei lah li-brei de-Rav Yirmiyah so the rabbis taught
Rav Yirmiyah or something the son of Rav Yirmiyah. כדברי האומר אשכול
וכל סביבותיו טמאין וכל הגת כולה טהורה ke-divrei ha-omer eshkol ve-chol sevivotav
tmein ve-chol ha-gat kula tehora to follow the position that it's only
its immediate surroundings are tamei but the rest of the wine press
is tahor. Okay what is interesting again there is that we are
moving back and forth between the issue of real טומאה וטהרה tumah
ve-tahara and יין נסך yayin nesech to some degree does it have
to mean because conceptually we see them as similar it just could
be you have exact realities of things absorbing in cold.
Know, but it might just be that the מציאות metzius is the
same, they're talking about wine presses and olive presses, but it actually
we do have seen the use of the language and the conceptual
structure of טומאה tumah by סתם יינם, stam yeinam, so it is
quite interesting that those parallels are being made. Okay, we thankfully, thankfully,
the last now דף daf and a half turn to classic כשרות
kashrus issues and we are done with the כשרות kashering of the
wine press and now we get to talk to sort of classic
כשרות kashrus and how do you כשר kasher כלים. keilim. Let's take
a look at the משנה. mishnah. הלוקח כלי תשמיש מן העובדי כוכבים.
halokeach k'lei tashmish min ha'ovdei kochavim. If somebody takes utensils, you know,
like means like cooking cookware
from a non-Jew
and presumably it's not brand new, it was used with טריפה. treif.
So how do you כשר kasher it? את שדרכו להטביל יטביל. es
shedarko l'hatbil yatbil. If it's something you normally dunk in a מקוה
mikvah you should dunk in a מקוה. mikvah. Now that's bizarre. What
does that mean? So we're going to see the way the גמרא
gemara is going to explain this. It's really quite buried in the
משנה, mishnah, but the גמרא gemara is going to say that we're
going to talk about two things. We're talking about כשרות kashering and
we're also talking about טבילת כלים. tevilas keilim. So right there's an
idea when you buy something even brand new from a non-Jew, you
have to be טובל tovel it and we're going to discuss that
in, you know, even if it's already כשר kosher or it's totally
brand new, and we'll discuss in the גמרא gemara where we learn
that from the פסוקים. pesukim. Okay, so the way they read this
משנה mishnah is, if it is something that was only used in
cold and doesn't need any כשרות, kashering, so all that it really
needs is טבילה, tevilah, so then you do טבילה. tevilah. להגעיל lehag'il
if however it is something that requires, it's a little tautologist, but
anyway, if it is something that is normally used with הגעלה hagalah
with boiling water, then יגעיל yag'il then you have to boil it.
Okay, this is the general principle of כבולעו כך פולטו k'bolo kach
polto that you have to do the reverse and opposite thing in
order to כשר kasher it. So if it's something that's normally used
with boiling hot water, but not in direct contact with the metal,
then you do it with boiling water. ללבן באור lelaben ba'or if
it is something that is normally whitened in the fire or can
be, you know, like something that's used directly on a fire like
a spit or a grill or frying pan, then ללבן באור lelaben
ba'or then you have to כשר kasher it by putting it directly
into the fire, getting it white hot with the fire. השפוד והאסכלא
hashapud v'ha'askala and then it gives you two examples about this: the
spit and the grate, מלבנן באור melabnan ba'or you have to get
them white hot in the fire. הסכין hasakin if you're dealing with
a knife and this could be a knife that actually didn't absorb
anything with hot, but it has a lot of grease, you know,
on its surface and, you know, and they did not have knives
that were like exactly the sharpness or the smoothness that we did,
so the stuff could really get, you know, the crud could really
get, you know, embedded in, so שפה והיא טהורה shafa v'hi tehora
you have to basically rub it like with some type of a
rough type of a thing to clean off the stuff that's stuck
on the surface and then you're okay. Alright, so the גמרא gemara
is going to quote a ברייתא braisa that expands on what was
very cryptic in the משנה, mishnah, this idea of טבילת כלים. tevilas
keilim. Okay, and this is going to be the basic גמרא gemara
about טבילת כלים. tevilas keilim. תניא, tanya, we taught a ברייתא, braisa,
וכולן צריכין טבילה בארבעים סאה. v'chulan tzrichin tevilah b'arba'im seah. All כלים
keilim that you buy from non-Jews, you know, that you need to
dunk 'em into a kosher מקוה mikvah of
forty סאה. seah. מנא הני מילי, mna hanei mili, where do you
get this from? אמר רבא אמר קרא, amar Rava amar kra, the
פסוק pasuk says by כלי מדין, klei Midyan, one of the classic
sources of how we know this idea or the classic source that
if you used cooking vessels with non-kosher that they absorb the non-kosher
and it's a problem because the תורה Torah basically says after they
took back the כלי מדין klei Midyan from this war against the
Midianites that אך את הזהב ואת הכסף את הנחשת את הברזל את
הבדיל ואת העופרת כל דבר אשר יבא באש תעבירו באש וטהר אך
במי נדה יתחטא וכל אשר לא יבא באש תעבירו במים. ach es
hazahav v'es hakesef es hanechoshes es habarzel es habdil v'es ha'oferes kol
davar asher yavo va'esh ta'aviru va'esh v'taher ach b'mei niddah yitchata v'chol
asher lo yavo va'esh ta'aviru vamayim. Okay, anything that can go in
the fire go in the fire, but you must be literally sprinkle
it with the ashes of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, and anything
that goes in the water goes in the water. So that's what
the so in the simple sense of those פסוקים pesukim we are
talking about, you know, about טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah because right afterwards,
you know, it says that you should, you know, cleanse your clothes,
you know, be טובל tovel your clothes and then you can come
into the camp. And they just came from a war and there
was all these dead that were in the war. So the simple
sense there's about טומאה וטהרה. tumah v'taharah. But then and that explains
the במי נדה יתחטא, b'mei niddah yitchata, sprinkle the ashes of the
פרה אדומה parah adumah because it came in contact with the dead.
But then the funny thing would be that what is this כל
אשר יבא באש תעבירו באש וטהר? kol asher yavo va'esh ta'aviru va'esh
v'taher? When did we ever find this idea that you need fire
as part of a process of making something טהור? tahor? So because
of that חז"ל chazal read it that we are not talking about
טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, we are actually talking about כשרות. kashering. And
the פסוק pasuk is saying anything that exactly what our משנה mishnah
said, anything that is normally used... Normally cooked with fire, you used
with fire, you have to pass through fire to make it כשר.
kosher. And anything that's worked with water, like you know you boil
and it's a pot, then you make it כשר kosher by putting
it in by boiling water. So we're not talking about טהרה, taharah,
we're talking about הכשר. kashering. Okay, that deals with the fire and
the water of the פסוק. pasuk. But what about this middle part
that says אך במי נדה יתחטא? ach b'mei nidah yitchata? Sprinkle the
ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. That clearly seems to be
טהרה. taharah. So the גמרא Gemara is going to say no, that
is referring to putting it in a מקוה, mikvah, and that's teaching
you this other הלכה. halacha. Not only do you have to כשר
kosher a כלי, kli, you have to put it in the מקוה.
mikvah. But nothing has to do with classic טומאה tumah and טהרה.
taharah. Right? So let's take a look at that. מנא הני מילי?
mana hani mili? We already know this from, אמר רב אדא בר
אהבה, amar Rav Ada bar Ahava, the פסוק pasuk says: כל דבר
אשר יבא באש תעבירו באש וטהר. kol davar asher yavo va'eish ta'aviru
va'eish v'taher. Anything that will go through the fire, you have to
pass through the fire,
וטהר v'taher and it will be pure. But the way this is
being read: הוסיף לך הכתוב טהרה אחרת. hosif l'cha hakatuv taharah acheret.
You have to do another act of purifying. Okay? So the תעבירו
באש ta'aviru va'eish is to כשר kosher it, וטהר v'taher and you
have to do another act and you have to dunk it in
the מקוה. mikvah. תני בר קפרא, tani Bar Kappara, Bar Kappara teaches
the ברייתא: braita: מתוך שנאמר
במי נדה, mitoch shene'emar b'mei nidah, which is the part I was
focusing on: אך במי נדה יתחטא, ach b'mei nidah yitchata, the ashes
of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. שומע אני שצריך הזיה שלישי ושביעי.
shomeia ani shetzarich hazaya shlishi v'shvi'i. It sounds like you need to
sprinkle the ashes on day three and seven, which is yes, that
is indeed what it sounds like. תלמוד לומר אך. talmud lomar ach.
חלק. chalak. No. The אך, ach, however, says: No, no, we don't
mean really the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. We're not
talking about טומאה tumah and טהרה. taharah. We're talking about something else
and not the ashes of the פרה אדומה. parah adumah. אם כן
מה תלמוד לומר במי נדה? im kein mah talmud lomar b'mei nidah?
So what does the waters of נדה, nidah, which normally means sprinkling
waters of the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, what does that mean? So
we're going to give it a totally non-פשט pshat read. מים שנדה
טובלת בהן. mayim shenidah tovelet bahen.
It's the waters that a נדה nidah would go into. So במי
נדה יתחטא b'mei nidah yitchata means: Purify in waters of a נדה
nidah that a נדה nidah would purify herself in. And what is
that? הוי אומר ארבעים סאה. hevei omer arbaim se'ah. 40 סאה. se'ah.
Of course, the irony is that the תורה Torah never says that
a woman, you know, who is a נדה nidah goes into the
מקוה. mikvah. Okay, but anyway, so that's how we're learning it. So
the fire and water is not a טהרה taharah process, that's הכשר
kashering from the טריפות. treifus. And the במי נדה b'mei nidah is
also not the ashes of פרה אדומה. parah adumah. It's also not
a טהרה taharah process. It is the מצוה mitzvah of טבילת כלים.
tevilat keilim. And because it is such a non-פשט pshat read of
the פסוקים, psukim, some ראשונים Rishonim think that it's אסמכתא asmachta and
it's דרבנן, d'rabbanan, but others very much do believe that it is
דאורייתא. d'Oraita. Okay,
and the גמרא Gemara certainly sounds like it's דאורייתא. d'Oraita. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says like this.
איצטריך למכתב וטהר ואיצטריך למכתב במי נדה. itztarich lemichtav v'taher v'itztarich lemichtav
b'mei nidah. Now we have two דרשות. drashot. One is the וטהר:
v'taher: you shall pass through the fire וטהר v'taher and you have
to do another טהרה taharah process, you have to do, you know,
טבילה. tevilah. And the other is במי נדה, b'mei nidah, that you
have to do the waters of a נדה, nidah, ארבעים סאה. arbaim
se'ah. So why did you need both?
אי כתב וטהר, ei katav v'taher, if it just said וטהר, v'taher,
הוה אמינא וטהר כל דהו. hava amina v'taher kol dahu. Any form,
even not a full מקוה. mikvah. Because you know sometimes you can
actually have, like מקואות mikvaot that could be less than ארבעים סאה
arbaim se'ah in some circumstances. If you took a look at תוספות,
Tosafot, okay, here's an irony: מים שנדה טובלת. mayim shenidah tovelet. תוספות
Tosafot says: אף על גב דרביעית סגי להטביל מחטין וצינורות מדאורייתא. af
al gav d'revi'it sagi l'hatvil machtin v'tzinnorot m'd'Oraita. Okay, so actually when
it comes to טבילת כלים, tevilat keilim, not טבילת כלים tevilat keilim
of cookware, but טבילת כלים tevilat keilim that a כלי kli became
טמא. tamei. You have a needle, a sewing needle, and it became
טמא. tamei. You can actually use a מקוה mikvah that's only a
רביעית, revi'it, that's only like three and a half ounces. Okay? You
do not need ארבעים סאה. arbaim se'ah. So when it comes to
real טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, you don't need ארבעים סאה. arbaim se'ah.
You, you know, it's enough for כלים keilim to have a very
small amount of water. אבל טבילת כלי מדין חידוש הוא ובעינן ארבעים
סאה. aval tevilat klei midyan chiddush hu v'ba'inan arbaim se'ah. But טבילת
כלי מדין, tevilat klei Midyan,
that's not about טומאה וטהרה, tumah v'taharah, it's about, let's say, changing
of identity, going from non-Jewish to Jewish. And therefore it needs like
a human type of a מקוה, mikvah, ארבעים סאה. arbaim se'ah. It's
a real change of identity, it's not just a removing of טומאה.
tumah. Okay, that's my little פירוש peirush on תוספות. Tosafot. Okay, so
that's what the גמרא Gemara says. If it had just said וטהר,
v'taher, I would have thought any form, you don't even need a
full מקוה. mikvah. כתב רחמנא במי נדה. katav Rachmana b'mei nidah. It
says במי נדה b'mei nidah that you need a full מקוה. mikvah.
ואי כתב רחמנא במי נדה, v'ei katav Rachmana b'mei nidah, if it
just said במי נדה, b'mei nidah, הוה אמינא הערב שמש כנדה. hava
amina he'erev shemesh k'nidah.
Like a נדה, nidah, it's not enough to go to the מקוה
mikvah to be totally טהור, tahor, you have to wait till sunset.
Okay, not in terms of being with her husband, but in terms
of, this is the, well actually, you know, in the תורה Torah
the נדה nidah would go to the מקוה mikvah at night, well
nowadays we also go at night after seven full days have passed.
Okay, and then she could go back and be with her husband,
but she would only, like anybody who goes to the מקוה mikvah
in terms of the טומאה וטהרה tumah v'taharah הלכות, halachos, in terms
of if she touches let's say תרומה, trumah, that. would have to
wait until the following nightfall to be totally טהור. Tahor. So if
it had just said נדה, Niddah, I might have thought you had
to wait until the following nightfall, so כתב רחמנא Kasav Rachmana ותהר
V'taher she become טהור Tahor לאלתר L'alter as soon as you put
it in the מקוה, Mikvah, that is all you need to do.
Okay, so this is the basis of טבילת כלים. Tvilas Keilim. אמר
רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar
Avuha said רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of רבה בר
אבוה Rabba bar Avuha ואפילו כלים חדשים במשמע V'afilu keilim chadashim b'mashma
once the תורה Torah is, it would even apply to brand new
כלים, Keilim, even though the
context embedded in the פסוקים, Psukim, the way we read the פסוקים
Psukim is all about kashering כלים, Keilim, but even if it would
be needed for brand new, and as we know, that's what we
do. How do you know that?
דהא ישנים ולבנן D'ha yeshanim v'libnan because old ones, after you, if
you when they got the כלי מדין, Klei Midyan, what would they
do? Right, if it was like a spit, you would put it
back in the fire, you would totally get out all the טרפות,
Treifus,
okay, ולבנן כחדשים דמו V'libnan k'chadashim damu that's like you totally remade
it, you put it back in the fire, it's like you made
it anew, ואפילו הכי בעי טבילה V'afilu hachi bei tveila and nevertheless
it requires טבילה. Tveila. Now, that's not such a good point because
you could have thought that the very fact that it's embedded in
means that once this is not just owned by non-Jews, but it
gets the identity of being a non-Jewish כלי Kli because טרפות Treifus
goes into it, then it needs a whole transformative process. You've got
to take the טרפות Treifus out and you've got to do a
טבילה Tveila to change its identity. But if it was only owned
by non-Jews and never used by them, never used with טרפות, Treifus,
it never got that identity, maybe you don't need anything. But once
you need something, maybe you need this whole process. Okay, and that
there are actually some ראשונים Rishonim that think because of the way
this is embedded in the פסוקים Psukim with kashering, that there is
a logical connection between them and there's actually a debate about can
you do טבילת כלים Tvilas Keilim before you do הכשר? Hechsher? You
buy a טריפה Treif כלי, Kli, can I do טבילה Tveila and
then and then and then kasher it afterwards? And תוספות Tosafos is
of the position in general, we're of the we פסקן Pasken that
yes, there are two independent things. One is kashering, one is טבילה,
Tveila, that's that's sort
of reinforced by the fact that the גמרא Gemara says טבילה Tveila
is even brand new כלים, Keilim, so therefore they're not really connected
at all. But there is another opinion that says no,
it's still is holding on to its non-Jewish identity if it's טריפה
Treif when you put it in the מקוה. Mikvah. It would be
like somebody converting, a man converting who goes into the מקוה Mikvah
without first doing a ברית מילה. Bris Milah. So if that מקוה
Mikvah is going to change its identity, it would have to be
free from its past. So you have to go ahead and first
kasher it and then put it in the מקוה. Mikvah. That's not
the way we פסקן. Pasken. But again, that shows a type of
a way in which these all might be talking about when it
really gets that identity through being טריפה, Treif, and that's not, however,
how we're פסקן. Pasken.
רב נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of רבה בר אבוה Rabba
bar Avuha is פסקן Paskening because he is saying it's even needed
for totally brand new כלים. Keilim. אפילו כלים חדשים במשמע דהא ישנים
ולבנן כחדשים דמו ואפילו הכי בעי טבילה. Afilu keilim chadashim b'mashma d'ha
yeshanim v'libnan k'chadashim damu v'afilu hachi bei tveila. Okay, so and that
is, as you all know, the הלכה. Halacha. מתקיף לה רב ששת
Maskif la Rav Sheshes רב ששת Rav Sheshes asked on this, אי
הכי אפילו זוזי דסרבא לנאמי? Ei hachi afilu zuzei d'sarva l'nami? If
it's really not based on טרפות, Treifus, if it's even brand new,
so let's say you buy some scissors from the non-Jew, should you
also need to put them in the
מקוה? Mikvah? אמר ליה כלי סעודה אמרה פרשה. Amar lei klei seuda
amra parsha. No, the תורה Torah happens to be talking about cookware,
silverware and so on. It's a גזירת הכתוב. Gzeiras Hakasuv. If you
want, and so it's true, it doesn't need to have absorbed טרפות,
Treifus, but it still has to be coming from the world of
טרפות. Treifus. If it's cookware, whatever, and it's owned by non-Jews, that's
associated with all the non-Jewish food, that's when it needs this type
of טבילה Tveila to change its identity. Just something that is unrelated
to that טריפה Treif world, that does not need the טבילה. Tveila.
So you don't actually have to cook טריפה Treif with it, but
it does have to be cookware. Okay,
or kitchenware. Alright. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה. Amar Rav
Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha.
By the way, in the הלכה Halacha is also it's only a
type of thing that has come in contact with food. So for
example, a can opener doesn't need טבילה Tveila because it only comes
in contact with the can. Alright, so it's only something which is
actually comes in contact with the food, so something that could become
טריפה Treif is basically the point, even if it's brand new.
Okay. אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה לא שנו אלא בלקוחין
כמעשה שהיה. Amar Rav Nachman amar Rabba bar Avuha lo shanu ela
b'lekuchin k'maaseh she'haya. This only applies if you purchase it, if you
become the owner of it, like the story with כלי מדין Klei
Midyan where they became they took it in battle and they became
the owner. אבל שאולין לא. Aval sheulin lo. But if you're only
borrowing it from the non-Jew, no, it's not becoming now a Jewish
vessel, so it can retain its non-Jewish identity, which is pretty interesting,
and you can go ahead and use it assuming it's כשר. Kosher.
רב יצחק בר יוסף זבן מנא דמר דמי עובדי כוכבים. Rav Yitzchak
bar Yosef zavan mana d'mar d'mei ovdei kochavim.
So רב יצחק בר יוסף. Rav Yitzchak bar Yosef. He bought a
vessel made out of like dried up animal dung, okay, from a
non-Jew. סבר לאטבולי Savar leatvulei he thought, well, you have to do
טבילה. Tevilah. Right, we haven't talked about the materials yet. אמר ליה
ההוא מדרבנן Amar leh hahu miderabbanan so one of the rabbis said,
יעקב שמיה Yaakov shemei and his name was יעקב, Yaakov, לדידי מפרשא
לי מיניה דרבי יוחנן Lididi mefarsha li minei deRabbi Yochanan no, it
was explained to me in the name of רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan,
כלי מתכות אמורין בפרשה. Klei matachot amorin baparashah. It's talking about metal,
right, it talks if it's metal, if it's if it's lead, if
it's this, if it's silver and so on. So it only applies
to metal, which is ironic, right, because if it is about, let's
say, pottery that's brand new, pottery can become totally tref, that can't
be kashered, but pottery doesn't need טבילה, Tevilah, wood doesn't need טבילה,
Tevilah, only metal needs. So we really are to some degree within
a little גזירת הכתוב Gzeras hakatuv type of a parameters here. This
is hard to give any conceptual explanation to. Okay. אמר רב אשי
הני כלי זכוכית הואיל וכי נשתברו יש להן תקנה כלי מתכות דמו.
Amar Rav Ashi hani klei zechuchit ho'il vechi nishtabru yesh lahen takanah
klei matachot damu.
So the only thing in addition to metal is glass. Because what
happens with glass is if it breaks, you know, you can go
ahead and by firing it up you can fix it. So it's
like metal that you can use heat to shape it, so therefore
halachically we will treat it as metal and rabbinically that requires טבילה
Tevilah as well. Now קוניא, Kunya, what about pottery ware that is
has is glazed, okay, רש״י Rashi has glazed with lead, which explains
lead poisoning in the ancient world. So פליגי בה רב אחא ורבינא,
Pligi bah Rav Acha uRavina, that's debated. חד אמר כתחילתו, Chad amar
ketchilato, like its original, meaning it's basically pottery, you don't go by
the glaze at the end, וחד אמר כסופו, Vechad amar kesofo, no,
you go by the end and that glaze actually is a lead
glaze and therefore it's defined as lead and needs טבילה, Tevilah, והלכתא
כסופו, Vehilchata kesofo,
and we rule it goes by the end. Now it is for
that reason, you know, that many people have the practice of being
טובל, Tovel, you know, all of their actual pottery dishes. However, that
glaze is not the lead glaze that the גמרא Gemara was talking
about, that glaze often one of the main ingredients is silica, which
is a type of like a glass, okay, so it's true that
glass also but even glass itself was only a rabbinic extension, and
it's also a very, very thin glaze. So it is, you know,
not definitely
it is seriously debated whether that requires that falls into this category
that the גמרא Gemara refers to in terms of pottery, and I
certainly do not feel that your standard, you know, pottery dishes or
whatever, you know, just just standard dishes do not need טבילה Tevilah
in my opinion, but many people do do טבילה Tevilah at least
without a ברכה. Brachah. Okay.
Now איבעיא להו, Iba'ya lehu, they asked the question, משכנתא מה, Mashkanta
mah, what's the story if somebody took it as a as collateral,
okay, from a non-Jew? Do you and then do you know do
you have to be טובל Tovel it? So אמר מר בר רב
אשי אבא משכני ליה עובד כוכבים כסא דכספא, Amar Mar bar Rav
Ashi Abba mashkanei leh oved kochavim kasa dechaspa,
so
my father took a collateral from a non-Jew from a loan, a
goblet of silver, ואטבליה, Veatvuleih,
and he dunks it in the מקוה, Mikvah, ואישתי ביה, Veishti beih,
and he drank from it personally, he, you know, that sometimes goes
to the rule that you could make use out of your out
of a collateral that you had seized until the loan was payoff
paid off. ולא ידענא אי משום דקסבר משכנתא כזביני דמי, Velo yadana
ei mishum dekasavar mashkanta kezveini dami, I don't know if he holds
that in general when something is being held as collateral and therefore
might actually be taken for payment of the debt, it's already considered
like you've purchased it, and that's why he required it. So as
a general rule, yes, collateral would require it. אי משום דחזייה לעובד
כוכבים דדעתיה לשקועי, Ei mishum dechazyeih leoved kochavim dedateih leshiku'ei, or because
he saw that the non-Jew's intention was basically not to pay the
debt and let him keep the the goblet as payment for the
debt, so it was a special case, but from that you cannot
learn the general rule. Okay, so we will end here for today,
so because this is a nice place to end, it finishes the
discussions of טבילת כלים, Tevilat kelim, and so tomorrow we will get
to the second part of the משנה, Mishna, which is the classic
discussion of kashering כלים kelim that were absorbed through heat and the
use of heat for kashering. Okay.